Eleanor Taft Tilton Papers
© 2004 University of Connecticut
Eleanor Taft Tilton Papers.
1939-1976.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Tilton, Eleanor Taft.
5.5 linear feet.
Eleanor Taft Tilton, daughter of Dr. Charles and Martha Jarvis Taft, was born in Hartford, Connecticut on 1 January 1901. She attended Vassar and Barnard Colleges, but did not earn a degree. She married Arthur can Riper Tilton; he was employed by the Hartford Fire Insurance Company for many years. Mrs. Tilton died on 26 March 1984.
MSS19790018
Biography
Eleanor Taft Tilton, daughter of Dr. Charles and Martha Jarvis Taft, was born in Hartford, Connecticut on 1 January 1901. She attended Vassar and Barnard Colleges, but did not earn a degree. She married Arthur can Riper Tilton; he was employed by the Hartford Fire Insurance Company for many years.
Mrs. Tilton was involved in civic and state affairs. She was an active opponent of the I-84 extension (Bushnell Park Connector); she was a member of the Election Laws Commission, PTA, served as secretary to the Fine Arts Commission, and as president of the Hartford League of Women Voters. Mrs. Tilton was also known for her outspoken support of the separation of church and state: Tilton v. Meskill, Tilton v. Finch, and Tilton v. Richardson.
Mrs. Tilton died on 26 March 1984.
Scope and Content
The collection reflects Mrs. Tilton's active interest in civic and state affairs. The collection includes correspondence, reports, maps, plans, newspaper clippings, notebooks, minutes, agendas, and financial records concerning the following topics: development of Hartford, Connecticut; separation of church and state; education; American Civil Liberties Union; Thomas J. Dodd; elections; environmental issues; and world affairs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in a single series divided into twelve sections:
Bushnell Park Connector ( undated, 1947-1973 ) —contains material concerning the development plans of Hartford, the different committees on which Mrs. Tilton served, as well as reference material. Major topics include the Commission on the City Plan, the Committee for Hartford, the Connecticut Capitol Center, and the State Capital Government Center Committee. The section includes correspondence with Governor John Dempsey and others, maps and plans, newspaper clippings, and reports.
Church-State Separation ( undated, 1961-1976 ) —consists of materials related to Mrs. Tilton's fight to uphold the separation of church and state. Within the section are materials associated with the American Civil Liberties Union; Americans United for Separation of Church and State; Church-State, a monthly review (1961-1975); the Connecticut Civil Liberties Union Church-State Committee; court cases (1968-1973); the issue of educational vouchers (1970-1973) Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965; legislative acts (1969-1973); and shared time, dual enrollment (1964-1968). The section also includes correspondence, publications and newspaper clippings, as well as writings of Mrs. Tilton including: biographical information, drafts and copies of correspondence, personal notebooks, letters to editors, and drafts of reports.
Citizen's Charter Commission ( undated, 1953 ) —consists of correspondence and newspaper clippings relating to the commission.
Civil Liberties Union ( undated, 1965-1973 ) —contains materials pertaining to the American Civil Liberties Union (1965-1972) and the Connecticut Civil Liberties Union. Topics include birth control, Black Panthers and Knights of Columbus.
Thomas J. Dodd ( undated, 1961-1967 ) —contains materials collected by Mrs. Tilton relating to Thomas Dodd and his political career. The materials include correspondence about Dodd (1963), newspaper clippings, letters to editors (1962-1963) and notes.
Election Laws Commission ( 1939, 1941 ) —consists of reports and their drafts.
Environmental issues ( undated, 1951-1954 ) —contains materials which deal with the Submerged Lands Act (1951-1954); steel mills in Connecticut; timber bill, H.R. 4646 (1954); and the Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act (1953-1954).
Fine Arts Commission ( undated, 1957-1970 ) —contains correspondence, membership lists, minutes, agendas, reports, rules and procedures, and outgoing correspondence.
League of Women Voters ( 1948-1972 ) —consists of a single file of material received by Mrs. Tilton from the League.
Personal Papers ( undated, 1945-1973 ) —consists of material relating to family matters and personal interests. Included are correspondence, family and financial papers (1946-1947), newspaper clippings (1967-1972), her work as a real estate broker (1946-1950) and two scrapbooks of clippings (1953-1954).
Adlai Stevenson contains an undated interview with Governor Stevenson by Mrs. Tilton and a 1953 letter.
World Affairs ( undated, 1945-1963 ) —consists of information on world issues and affairs, publication from the Department of State (1945), Foreign Policy Association materials, clippings (1962-1963), peace and disarmament and the United Nations (1945).
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut history and politics. See especially the papers of Thomas J. Dodd, Connecticut Civil Liberties Union, Henry Gray, Audrey Beck, Chase Going Woodhouse. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
City planning--Connecticut.; Express highways--Environmental aspects--Connecticut.; Municipal charters.; Municipal government--Connecticut.; Women in politics--Connecticut.; Voting--Connecticut.; Voting--Societies, etc.; Women in real estate--Connecticut.; Environmental protection--Connecticut.; Civic centers--Connecticut.; Civic improvement--Connecticut.; Election law--Connecticut.; Church and state--Connecticut.; Educational law and legislation--United States.; Actions and defenses--Connecticut.; Political parties--United States.; Political crimes and offenses--United States.; Catholics--United States.; Men--United States--Societies and clubs.; Friendly societies--United States.; Submerged lands--Law and legislation--United States.; Peace movements.; Disarmament.; Civil rights--Connecticut.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Maps.; Financial Records.; Minutes.; Press releases.; Notes.; Scrap-Books.; Interviews.; Lawsuits.; Speeches.; Civil actions.
Occupations:
Civic activist.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Joan Tilton Kenney on 26 February 1980.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Papers, undated, 1939-1976
  - Bushnell Park Connector (undated, 1947-1973)
    - Alternate locations studied, Summary, 1965 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Bushnell Park—informal committee, undated, 1962-1964 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - Commission on the City Plan
      - “Coordinated Transportation for Hartford”, 1947 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
      - “Hartford plans for tomorrow”, 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
      - “Renewal programs for downtown”, undated (Box 1:, Folder 6)
      - Reports, 1961 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
      - “Trumbull Street renewal area”, 1961 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - Committee for Hartford
      - Bushnell Plaza Project, 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, 1960-1969 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
      - Greater Hartford Chamber of Commerce Annual Reports, 1962, 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
      - Meetings—minutes and agendas, 1960-1964 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
      - Members and committees, undated (Box 1:, Folder 13)
      - Pamphlets, undated (Box 1:, Folder 14)
      - Reports—drafts, 1964 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
      - Reports and records of State Government Center, 1964-1965 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
      - Statements, Programs, 1960-1965 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
    - Concerning Bushnell Park preservation, 1965 (Box 2:, Folder 18)
    - Connecticut Capitol Center, 1967 (Box 2:, Folder 19)
      - Rogers, Taliafern, Kostritsky & Lamb, 1966 (Box 2:, Folder 20)
    - Connecticut, Commission, Report of the, 1967 (Box 2:, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, 1952-1967 (Box 2:, Folder 22-24)
    - Court of Common Council, 1964-1967 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
    - Dempsey, Governor John—correspondence, 1964-1967 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
    - Hartford Government Center—draft, undated (Box 2:, Folder 27)
    - Legislation and legal papers, 1961-1967 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
    - Maps and plans (oversize), undated (Box 12)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1957-1970 (Box 2:, Folder 29-31)
    - Noel, Con—“City's dilemma—more highways or mass transit”, 1966 (Box 2:, Folder 32)
    - Reference, undated, 1966 (Box 2:, Folder 33)
    - Senate Bill 1111, 1967 (Box 2:, Folder 34)
    - State Capitol Government Center Committee
      - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 2:, Folder 35)
      - Minutes, agendas, memoranda, 1965-1966 (Box 2:, Folder 36-38)
      - Planning subcommittee, 1965 (Box 2:, Folder 39)
      - Planning subcommittee, 1965 (Box 3:, Folder 40)
      - Reports, 1966 (Box 3:, Folder 41)
      - Technical documentation report, 1967 (Box 3:, Folder 42)
      - Tilton, Eleanor Taft
        - Correspondence, 1961-1967 (Box 3:, Folder 43-47)
        - Notes, undated (Box 3:, Folder 48)
        - Reports, statements, 1963, 1965 (Box 3:, Folder 49)
    - West End Civic Association, undated, 1973 (Box 3:, Folder 50)
  - Church-State Separation (undated, 1961-1976)
    - American Civil Liberties Union, Church-State Committee
      - Memoranda, 1964-1974 (Box 3:, Folder 51)
      - Minutes and agenda, 1964-1976 (Box 3:, Folder 52)
      - Religious broadcasting, 1971 (Box 3:, Folder 53)
      - Reports, Committee roster, 1964-1973 (Box 3:, Folder 54)
    - American United for Separation of Church and State
      - Correspondence, addresses, 1965-1970 (Box 3:, Folder 55)
      - Publications, 1961-1970 (Box 3:, Folder 56)
    - Article reprints, 1970-1971 (Box 3:, Folder 57)
    - Cartoons, humor, undated (Box 3:, Folder 58)
    - Catholic schools and colleges—clippings, 1965-1973 (Box 3:, Folder 59)
    - Connecticut Civil Liberties Union, Church-State Committee (Box 5)
      - Church-State, 1967 (Box 5:, Folder 60)
      - Form letters, memoranda, 1963-1971 (Box 5:, Folder 61)
      - Publications, news releases, 1969, 1972 (Box 5:, Folder 62)
      - Reports, 1970, 1971 (Box 5:, Folder 63)
      - “Wake Up Connecticut” drafts, undated (Box 5:, Folder 64)
    - Connecticut General Assembly, 1971-1973 (Box 5:, Folder 65)
    - Constitutions: United States, Connecticut, undated (Box 5:, Folder 66)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1973 (Box 5:, Folder 67-68)
    - Court Cases
      - Briefs, motions, 1969-1972 (Box 5:, Folder 69)
      - Davis v. Sanders, 1972-1973 (Box 5:, Folder 70)
      - Flast v. Cohen, 1968 (Box 5:, Folder 71)
      - Johnson v. Sanders, 1969-1972 (Box 5:, Folder 72)
      - Tilton v. Finch, 1969-1971 (Box 5:, Folder 73)
      - Tilton v. Richardson, 1970-1971 (Box 5:, Folder 74)
    - Educational vouchers
      - Correspondence, reports, 1970-1971 (Box 5:, Folder 75)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1970-1973 (Box 5:, Folder 76)
      - Preliminary report, 1970 (Box 5:, Folder 77)
    - Elementary and Secondary Education Bill (H2362, S370), 1965
      - Bill, fact sheet (Box 5:, Folder 78)
      - Correspondence (Box 5:, Folder 79)
      - Related material (Box 6:, Folder 80)
      - Statements (Box 6:, Folder 81)
    - Enfield, Connecticut pilot program, 1972-1973 (Box 6:, Folder 82)
    - Legislative acts re aid to private schools, 1969-1973 (Box 6:, Folder 83)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1965-1973 (Box 6:, Folder 84-92)
    - New York complaints, 1966 (Box 6:, Folder 93)
    - Notebooks, church-state, undated, 1969-1970 (Box 6:, Folder 94)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity—St. Marin de Porres program proposal, 1964-1965 (Box 6:, Folder 95)
    - Parochial school aid, 1965-1971 (Box 6:, Folder 96)
      - Drawings, protests, undated (Box 6:, Folder 97)
    - Public Act 791, 1971, 1973 (Box 6:, Folder 98)
    - Public education in Connecticut, 1969-1971 (Box 6:, Folder 99)
    - Public education and religious liberty, 1969, 1973 (Box 6:, Folder 100)
    - Reference material
      - General, 1968-1972 (Box 7:, Folder 101)
      - Churches: their riches, revenues and immunities, 1969 (Box 7:, Folder 102)
      - “Connecticut education directory”, 1971 (Box 7:, Folder 103)
      - “Public funds for parochial schools?”, 1963 (Box 7:, Folder 104)
    - School prayer—newspaper clippings, 1963-1965 (Box 7:, Folder 105)
    - Senate Bill 657, 1969 (Box 7:, Folder 106)
    - Shared time, dual enrollment
      - Articles, newspaper clippings, 1963-1965 (Box 7:, Folder 107)
      - Correspondence, 1964-1968 (Box 7:, Folder 108)
      - Hearings before subcommittee, 1964 (Box 7:, Folder 109)
      - Notes, memoranda, 1965 (Box 7:, Folder 110)
      - Reports, statements, 1962-1965 (Box 7:, Folder 111)
    - Tilton, Eleanor Taft
      - Clippings, 1970 (Box 7:, Folder 112)
      - Correspondence, 1965-1971 (Box 7:, Folder 113)
      - Correspondence—drafts, undated, 1971 (Box 7:, Folder 114)
      - Letters to editors, 1965-1971 (Box 8:, Folder 115)
      - Notes, 1965-1971 (Box 8:, Folder 116)
      - Publications—drafts, undated (Box 8:, Folder 117)
      - Reports—drafts, 1970-1972 (Box 8:, Folder 118)
    - Transportation for parochial schools, undated, 1971 (Box 8:, Folder 119)
  - Citizen's Charter Commission (undated, 1953)
    - Correspondence, undated, 1953 (Box 8:, Folder 120)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1953 (Box 8:, Folder 121)
  - Civil Liberties Union (undated, 1965-1973)
    - American Civil Liberties Union, 1965, 1970-1971 (Box 8:, Folder 122)
      - Publications, 1965-1972 (Box 8:, Folder 123)
    - Connecticut Civil Liberties Union
      - Addresses, 1969-1972 (Box 8:, Folder 124)
      - Birth control, 1966-1970 (Box 8:, Folder 125)
      - Black Panthers, 1970 (Box 8:, Folder 126)
      - By-Laws, undated, 1970 (Box 8:, Folder 127)
      - Executive committee minutes, 1970-1971 (Box 8:, Folder 128)
      - Financial reports, budgets, 1970-1973 (Box 8:, Folder 129)
      - Hartford chapter, 1969-1973 (Box 8:, Folder 130)
      - Karpatkin, Marvin, 1969-1971 (Box 8:, Folder 131)
      - Knights of Columbus—newspaper clippings, 1971 (Box 8:, Folder 132)
      - Memoranda, 1965, 1970 (Box 8:, Folder 133)
      - News releases, 1969-1970 (Box 8:, Folder 134)
      - Other CCLU chapters, 1968-1971 (Box 8:, Folder 135)
      - Police department, undated, 1970 (Box 8:, Folder 136)
      - Policies, rules, undated, 1970 (Box 8:, Folder 137)
      - Publications, 1970-1973 (Box 8:, Folder 138)
      - State board
        - Memoranda, 1968-1971 (Box 8:, Folder 139)
        - Minutes and agenda, 19701971 (Box 8:, Folder 140)
      - Tilton, Eleanor Taft—correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 8:, Folder 141)
  - Thomas J. Dodd (undated, 1961-1967)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1967 (Box 9:, Folder 142)
    - Letters to editors, 1962-1963 (Box 9:, Folder 143)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1962-1967 (Box 9:, Folder 144-145)
    - Notes, undated (Box 9:, Folder 146)
    - Publications, 1961-1963 (Box 9:, Folder 147)
    - Tilton, Eleanor Taft—correspondence, undated, 1963 (Box 9:, Folder 148)
  - Election Laws Commission (1939, 1941)
    - Reports, 1939, 1941 (Box 9:, Folder 149-150)
    - Report—draft, 1941 (Box 9:, Folder 151)
  - Environmental issues (undated, 1951-1954)
    - Analysis of aye and nay votes, 83rd Congress, 1953 (Box 9:, Folder 152)
    - Outer Continental Shelf Lands Act
      - Amendment to, 1954 (Box 9:, Folder 153)
      - Public Law 212, HR5154, 1953 (Box 9:, Folder 154)
    - Steel mills in Connecticut, undated (Box 9:, Folder 155)
    - Submerged Lands Act
      - Amendment to, 1953 (Box 9:, Folder 156)
      - Connecticut schools—statistics, 1952-1953 (Box 9:, Folder 157)
      - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 9:, Folder 158)
      - Correspondence—drafts, undated, 1953 (Box 9:, Folder 159)
      - Hearing before Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs, 82nd Congress, 1952 (Box 9:, Folder 160)
      - Letters to editors, 1953-1954 (Box 9:, Folder 161)
      - Minority views, 1953 (Box 9:, Folder 162)
      - Newspaper clippings and articles, 1952, 1953 (Box 9:, Folder 163)
      - Public Law 31, HR4198, 1953 (Box 9:, Folder 164)
      - Remarks of Hon. Lister Hill, 1951 (Box 10:, Folder 165)
      - Remarks of Hon. Paul H. Douglas, 1953 (Box 10:, Folder 166)
      - Report from the Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs, 1953 (Box 10:, Folder 167)
      - Statements, undated, 1953 (Box 10:, Folder 168)
      - Superior Court, complaints to, 1954 (Box 10:, Folder 169)
      - Writings, undated (Box 10:, Folder 170)
    - Timber bill, HR4646, 1954 (Box 10:, Folder 171)
  - Fine Arts Commission (undated, 1957-1970)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1970 (Box 10:, Folder 172)
    - Members, undated, 1970 (Box 10:, Folder 173)
    - Minutes, agendas, reports, 1962-1970 (Box 10:, Folder 174)
    - Rules and procedures, undated, 1957 (Box 10:, Folder 175)
    - Tilton, Eleanor Taft—correspondence, 1962-1970 (Box 10:, Folder 176)
  - League of Women Voters (1948-1972)
    - League of Women Voters, 1948, 1961, 1970-1972 (Box 10:, Folder 177)
  - Personal Papers (undated, 1945-1973)
    - Bowles, Chester—speech, 1945 (Box 10:, Folder 178)
    - Connecticut C.I.O. convention, 1954 (Box 10:, Folder 179)
    - Correspondence, 1948, 1967-1971 (Box 10:, Folder 180)
    - Family papers, 1946-1947, 1971 (Box 10:, Folder 181)
    - Financial records, undated, 1946-1947 (Box 10:, Folder 182)
    - Leaflets and pamphlets, undated, 1971-1972 (Box 10:, Folder 183)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated, 1967-1972 (Box 10:, Folder 184)
    - Notes, undated (Box 10:, Folder 185)
    - Real estate
      - Correspondence, 1946-1950 (Box 10:, Folder 186)
        - Drafts, 1947-1950 (Box 10:, Folder 187)
      - Notes, agreements of sale, 1946-1949 (Box 10:, Folder 188)
    - Scrapbook (2), 1953-1954 (Box 10:, Folder 189)
    - State politics, 1971, 1972 (Box 10:, Folder 190)
    - Vassar College, 1971-1973 (Box 10:, Folder 191)
    - Women's groups, undated, 1945-1948 (Box 10:, Folder 192)
  - Adlai Stevenson (undated, 1953)
    - Interview with, undated (Box 11:, Folder 193)
    - Letters, 1953 (Box 11:, Folder 194)
  - World Affairs (undated, 1945-1963)
    - Department of State—publications, 1945 (Box 11:, Folder 195)
    - Foreign Policy Association, undated, 1948, 1951 (Box 11:, Folder 196)
    - Iceland, Russia, undated (Box 11:, Folder 197)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1962-1963 (Box 11:, Folder 198)
      - Congo/Katanga, 1962-1963 (Box 11:, Folder 199)
    - Peace and disarmament, undated, 1945 (Box 11:, Folder 200)
    - United Nations, undated, 1945 (Box 11:, Folder 201)